E. B. O'Callaghan Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
E. B. O'Callaghan Papers 1830-1876 (bulk 1845-1860)
MSS35014
O'Callaghan, E. B. (Edmund Bailey), 1797-1880
2,000 items
20 containers
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physician, historian, and bibliographer. Correspondence pertaining primarily to O'Callaghan's career as a physician, legislator in Lower Canada, and editor of the Montreal Vindicator. Also concerns bibliographic matters including records of New York state, rare bibliographic Americana, editions of the Bible, and material relating to America found in European archives. Includes a draft of his History of New Netherland (1846-1848).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen, Edward G.--Correspondence.; Alofsen, Solomon, 1808-1876--Correspondence.; Armstrong, Edward, 1846-1928--Correspondence.; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891--Correspondence.; Beach, Elizabeth T. Porter--Correspondence.; Beck, Theodric Romeyn, 1791-1855--Correspondence.; Brodhead, John Romeyn, 1814-1873--Correspondence.; Brown, John Carter, 1797-1874--Correspondence.; Deane, Charles, 1813-1889--Correspondence.; Drake, Samuel Gardner, 1798-1875--Correspondence.; Draper, Lyman Copeland, 1815-1891--Correspondence.; Ewbank, Thomas, 1792-1870--Correspondence.; Fabre, Hector, 1834-1901--Correspondence.; Fabre, Édouard Raymond, 1799-1854--Correspondence.; Garneau, F.-X. (François-Xavier), 1809-1866--Correspondence.; Gowans, William, 1803-1870--Correspondence.; Harris, Thaddeus William, 1795-1856--Correspondence.; Haven, Samuel F. (Samuel Foster), 1806-1881--Correspondence.; Hoadly, Charles J. (Charles Jeremy), 1828-1900--Correspondence.; Lenox, James, 1800-1880--Correspondence.; Livermore, George, 1809-1865--Correspondence.; Mackenzie, William Lyon, 1795-1861--Correspondence.; Martin, Benj. N. (Benjamin Nicholas), 1816-1883--Correspondence.; Moore, George Henry, 1823-1892--Correspondence.; Murphy, Henry Cruse, 1810-1882--Correspondence.; O'Callaghan, E. B. (Edmund Bailey), 1797-1880.; O'Callaghan, E. B. (Edmund Bailey), 1797-1880. History of New Netherland. 1846-1848.; Papineau, Louis Joseph, 1786-1871--Correspondence.; Parkman, Francis, 1823-1893--Correspondence.; Perrault, Louis, 1807-1866--Correspondence.; Richardson, Charles Benjamin, 1832-1891--Correspondence.; Shea, John Gilmary, 1824-1892--Correspondence.; Todd, Alpheus, 1821-1884--Correspondence.; Valentine, D. T. (David Thomas), 1801-1869--Correspondence.; Ward, Townsend, 1817?-1885--Correspondence.; Whitehead, William A. (William Adee), 1810-1884--Correspondence.
Organizations
Lower Canada. Legislature. House of Assembly.; New York (State). Secretary's Office.
Subjects
Americana--Bibliography.; Archives--Europe.; Canadian newspapers.; Editions.
Places
Lower Canada--Politics and government.; New York (State)--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
Titles
Bible.; Montreal vindicator (Newspaper)
Occupations
Archivists.; Bibliographers.; Historians.; Journalists.; Legislators--Lower Canada.; Physicians.
Provenance
The papers of E. B. O'Callaghan, physician and historian, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1904.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of E. B. O'Callaghan are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1797, Feb. 28 Born, Mallow (near Cork), Ireland
1820 Began study of medicine, Paris, France
1823 Emigrated to Canada to complete studies; admitted to medical practice
1830 Moved from Quebec to Montreal, Canada
1834 Became editor of Montreal Vindicator
1835 Elected to assembly of Upper Canada from Yamaska
1837 Participated in revolutionary action at St. Denis; fled Canada to avoid prosecution and settled in Albany, N. Y.
1837 1848 Practiced medicine
1846 1848 Published History of New Netherland. New York: D. Appleton. 2 vols.
1848 1870 Devoted full time to editing New York state records
1850 1851 Published The Documentary History of the State of New York. Albany, N.Y.: Weed, Parsons. 4 vols.
1852(?) 1870 Edited colonial archives while attached to the office of the New York secretary of state
1870 1877 Moved to New York, N.Y., to arrange and translate the municipal archives
1880, May 29 Died, New York, N.Y
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edmund Bailey O'Callaghan (1797-1830), span the years 1830-1876, with the bulk of the material falling between 1845 and 1860. The papers consist of correspondence, a partial draft of O'Callaghan's History of New Netherland, lists, records, and bibliographical material.
O'Callaghan's diversified career as historian, bibliographer, legislator, physician, and journalist is only partially documented by this collection. After emigrating from Ireland in 1823, O'Callaghan became prominent in Canadian politics and was associated with the revolutionary party. At the same time he was active in the founding of the Society of the Friends of Ireland and was editor of the Montreal Vindicator. His political career in Canada reached its zenith when, in 1835, he was elected to the assembly of Upper Canada. His political career, however, was cut short by his participation in the Insurrection of 1837. With a reward offered for his capture, O'Callaghan found it expedient to flee to the United States. The Canadian phase of O'Callaghan's career is survived by only one document, but there are references to his activities in Canada in later correspondence, particularly with William Lyon MacKenzie.
O'Callaghan's first years in the United States were taken up with the practice of medicine and with editing the Northern Light, an industrial journal. Apparently in connection with the latter occupation, O'Callaghan had reason to examine the state records of New York. Finding a wealth of material among them, O'Callaghan embarked upon a new career as historian and bibliographer. In 1846 he published the first volume of his History of New Netherland. Despite financial losses on that volume, he came out with a second in 1849. The draft of volume two (books 4-6 and appendices) is present in his papers, as well as related correspondence.
As a result of this work O'Callaghan was commissioned to edit the Documentary History of the State of New York. A voluminous amount of correspondence concerning the collection of historical material on New York is contained in the collection. Additional correspondence deals with other bibliographic matters, with Americana rarities, editions of the Bible, and O'Callaghan's duties in the office of the secretary of state of New York.
Prominent correspondents include Solomon Alofsen, Edward G. Allen, Edward Armstrong, George Bancroft, Elizabeth T. Porter Beach, Theodric Romeyn Beck, John Romeyn Brodhead, John Carter Brown (1797-1874), Charles Deane, Samuel Gardner Drake, Lyman Copeland Draper, Thomas Ewbank, Édouard Raymond Fabre, Hector Fabre, F.-X. Garneau, William Gowans, Thaddeus William Harris, Samuel F. Haven, Charles J. Hoadly, James Lenox, George Livermore, William Lyons MacKenzie, Benj. N. Martin, Gregory Henry Moore, Henry Cruse Murphy, Francis Parkman, Louis Joseph Papineau, Louis Perrault, Charles Benjamin Richardson, John Gilmary Shea, Alpheus Todd, D. T. Valentine, Townsend Ward, and William A. Whitehead.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized chronologically with drafts of the History of New Netherland files at the end.
Container List
- 1830, Jan. 18-1845, May 13 (Box 1)
- 1845, May 15-1846, Dec. 18 (Box 2)
- 1847, Jan. 2-1848, July 26 (Box 3)
- 1848, July 31-1850, Sept. 9 (Box 4)
- 1850, Sept. 12-1851, Aug. 19 (Box 5)
- 1851, Aug. 20-1852, June 9 (Box 6)
- 1852, June 11-1853, Apr. 2 (Box 7)
- 1853, Apr. 3-1854, Apr. 10 (Box 8)
- 1854, Apr. 11-Nov. 3 (Box 9)
- 1854, Nov. 4-1855, Oct. 1 (Box 10)
- 1855, Oct. 4-1856, Oct. 15 (Box 11)
- 1856, Oct. 21-1857, Sept. 5 (Box 12)
- 1857, Sept. 6-1858, Apr. 26 (Box 13)
- 1858, Apr. 27-Dec.. 21 (Box 14)
- 1858, Dec. 22-1859, June 6 (Box 15)
- 1859, June 8-1860, Feb. 6 (Box 16)
- 1860, Feb. 7-Sept.. 6 (Box 17)
- 1860, Sept. 7-1876, Feb. 7 (Box 18)
- History of New Netherland (drafts) (Box 19)
  - Vol. 2, books 4 and 5 (Box 19)
  - Vol. 2, book 6 (Box 20)
  - Appendices (Box 20)